Dane Rudhyar Papers
Dane Rudhyar Papers
1919-1973
Rudhyar, Dane, 1895-1985.
3.75 linear ft.
Papers of the American composer, painter, philosopher. Correspondence, and manuscript and published articles, books, and lectures relating to astrology, consciousness, the occult, self-realization, and theosophy.
149743
Biographical History
Dane Rudhyar (1895-1985), born Daniel Chennevière in Paris, was an author, composer and humanistic astrologer. Rudhyar studied at the Sorbonne, moved to New York in 1916, and became an American citizen in 1926. Although respected in astrological and New Age circles, he did not become generally well-known until the 1970s, when mainstream publisher Penguin Books published his The Practice of Astrology. Over the course of his life he wrote more than forty books and hundreds of articles on astrology and spirituality.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Dane Rudhyar Papers consist of writings, artwork, printed material, and published material by and about Rudhyar.
Arrangement of the Collection
Series are arranged in no particular order, but within each series material is arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Music; Religion and philosophy; Rudhyar, Dane, 1895-1985.; Authors, American.; Philosophers -- United States.; Astrology.; Consciousness.; Human beings.; Occultism.; Occultists -- United States.; Self (Philosophy); Self-realization.; Spiritual life.; Theosophy.; Articles.; Lectures.; Manuscripts for publication.; Authors.; Occultists.; Philosophers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Comfort, Will Levington (Box 1)
  - Council, Paul, popular astrology (Box 1)
  - Jones, Marc Edmund (Box 1)
  - Kirsch, James (Box 1)
  - Kunkel, Fritz (Box 1)
  - Lewi, Grant, ed. Horoscope (Box 1)
  - Miller, Henry, 1945; 1960; 2 items, 1 copy (Box 1)
  - Mott, Francis J. (Box 1)
  - —, Paul (Box 1)
  - re: Modern man's conflicts (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Aryan root-race and its sub-races, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Ascension of man, 1944 (Box 1)
    - "Astrologer" surveys modern thought, undated (Box 1)
    - Call to occultists and theosophists, undated (Box 1)
    - Challenge of true philosophy, undated (Box 1)
    - Circuits of the moon, 1943 (Box 1)
    - Civilization as food, 1925 (Box 1)
    - Cosmic ideas in art, undated (Box 1)
    - Declaration of human interdependence, 1943 (Box 1)
    - Descent into flesh, undated (Box 1)
    - Descent of power: an Aquarian key to the world in the making, 1946? (Box 1)
    - Easter meditation on Pluto, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Film music for all men, undated (Box 1)
    - Framework of personality: The meridian polarities, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Great American tradition, 1943 (Box 1)
    - Great stations of life and truth, undated (Box 1)
    - Light which shineth in darkness, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Lure of cosmic consciousness, 1922 (Box 1)
    - Make way for creative men!, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Messengers of the new life, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Mind on the threshold, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Mystery of the 'first breath', 1946 (Box 1)
    - Mystery of the seed, undated (Box 1)
    - Mystery of the sun, 1943 (Box 1)
    - New mysticism of science, 1937 (Box 1)
    - New sovereignty, 1945 (Box 1)
    - New year for a new world, 1943 (Box 1)
    - On the death of war heroes, 1942 (Box 1)
    - Organic democracy the answer to totalitarianism, 1943 (Box 1)
    - Our field and our purpose of action, 1924 (Box 1)
    - Our Piscean heritage and the task ahead for 'These Americas', 1943 (Box 1)
    - Power in defeat: The underground, 1945 (Box 1)
    - Practice in consideration, 1946? (Box 1)
    - Problems of the emotional life, 1948 (Box 1)
    - Production for plenty - for all, by all, 1943 (Box 1)
    - Rebirth of Mercury, 1943 (Box 1)
    - Reconstruction in truth, 1945 (Box 1)
    - Secret doctrine, 1923 (Box 1)
    - Seed for greater living
      - 1955-1956, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1957-1963, undated, 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Steps to astrological wisdom, 1945-1946; 1967-1968; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Studies in modern psychology: The education to personality, 1946-1947 (Box 2)
    - Study of psychological complexes, 1947 (Box 2)
    - Synthesis - solidarity - service, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Thomas Paine, father of western democracy, undated (Box 2)
    - Toward the man of plentitude, 1960 (Box 2)
    - Transfer of destiny, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Trinity of diseases, undated (Box 3)
    - Way of creative accomplishment, 1944 (Box 3)
    - Way Through: Twelve basic challenges and tests of individual existence, 1961 (Box 3)
    - When end meets beginning, 1945 (Box 3)
    - Where do we stand, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Why I wrote Fire out of stone, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Work of civilization, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Books
    - Astrology of America's destiny, circa 1973
      - First draft, not used, manuscript (Box 3)
      - Manuscript, holograph (Box 3)
      - Setting copy (Box 3)
      - Corrected galley (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous production material (Box 3)
    - Faith that gives meaning to victory
      - Manuscript, 1942; 1943; holograph (Box 4)
      - Revisions, 1948 (Box 4)
    - Gifts of the spirit, undated; manuscript (holograph and typescript copy) (Box 4)
    - Gospel to individuals, undated; manuscript (holograph and typescript copy); 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Lovely little ghost, 1953; manuscript (holograph) (Box 4)
    - Meditations on universal themes (proposed), 1942-1946?; manuscript (holograph); 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Moon cycles and fortunes of life, 1946; published copy with revisions (Box 4)
    - New goals, 1945-1946
      - Manuscript, 5 chapters, holograph and typescript copy (Box 4)
      - Manuscript, 4 chapters, holograph and typescript copy (Box 5)
    - New mansions for new men, 1935-1936; manuscript (holograph and typescript copy); 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Of stars, sex, and Henry Miller, 1955; manuscript (holograph) (Box 5)
    - Rana: an epic narrative, manuscript (typescript copy); 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Transcendental movement in painting, 1939; manuscript (holograph); 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Triptych
      - Part I, Gifts of the spirit, 1945-1946; manuscript (holograph, typescript copy) and clipping (Box 5)
      - Part II, Challenges of the earth, 1946-1947; manuscript (holograph) (Box 5)
      - Part III, The Illumined road, 1947-1948; manuscript (holograph), original folder (Box 6)
    - When cosmic love awakens, 1953; manuscript (holograph) (Box 6)
  - Lectures
    - New images for modern times, 1954 (Box 6)
    - New symbols for a global society, 1966 (Box 6)
    - Quality of a creative leadership in the atomic age, 1954 (Box 6)
    - Transpersonal way and the religious attitude, 1954 (Box 6)
  - Lessons
    - Liberation through sound, 1931; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - About Rudhyar
    - Astrology of personality, 1937; comments (Box 6)
    - Faith that gives meaning to victory, undated (Box 6)
- Artwork by Rudhyar
  - "Storm gods," offset print, undated (Box 6)
- Printed material
  - By Rudhyar
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Minute scope, Nov/Dec 1963; Jan 1964 (Box 6)
    - Seed letter, Sep 1958 (Box 6)
  - About Rudhyar
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Morang, A. / Dane Rudhyar, pioneer in creative synthesis, 1939; 2 copies (Box 6)
    - Programs, lectures, etc. (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous
  - Dried petals (Box 6)
- Published material
  - By Rudhyar
    - Astrologie Aanleg en Karakter, 1950 (Box 7)
    - Faith that gives meaning to victory, 1943 (Box 7)
    - Fire out of the stone, circa 1963 (Box 7)
    - Gifts of the spirit, circa 1956 (Box 7)
    - Lunation cycle, circa 1967 (Box 7)
    - Modern man's conflicts, 1948 (Box 7)
    - New mansions for new men, 1946 (Box 7)
    - Rebirth of Hindu music, 1928; 2 copies (Box 7)
    - Rhapsodies, 1919 (Box 7)
    - Rhythm of human fulfillment, circa 1966; 2 copies (Box 7)
    - Roc enflamme, circa 1960 (Box 7)
    - Seed ideas, 2nd series: Will to destiny, circa 1930; 2 copies (Box 7)
  - By others
    - Bhagawad gita, 1910 (Box 8)
    - Henry Cowell, a record of his activities, 1934 (Box 8)
    - Edwin A. Fleisher collection of orchestral music in the Free Library of Philadelphia, 1945 (Box 8)
    - Merrill, Arch / Our goodly heritage, undated; signed by author (Box 8)